So let's start off with
that first seminal Steven
Blair paper from 1989 in JAMA,
in that they had about 10,000 men
and about 3,000 women or so.
And what's actually
interesting about this study,
and many others like it,
they typically follow the
individuals for years.
I believe in this actual study,
it was something like nine years,
and within that, several
hundred people actually died.
And so it's a bit morbid, I understand,
but it makes the science
incredibly compelling
because we can look at a number of people,
wait for several of them to die,
and then come back and say,
"What actually was different
between those people who died
at baseline versus those who didn't die?
You know, again, at
baseline and after that."
And so we can get really
strong insights about
what predicted death.
Now what they found in this initial study,
and this is directly
from the paper itself,
was after age adjustment,
so again, they would kind
of factor in their age,
and say, "Let's take that
out of the equation."
So after age-adjusted,
all-cause mortality,
meaning died for any reason,
declined directly across fitness levels.
So as you reduced your fitness,
you increased your
all-cause mortality risk.
And it went from a number of
what is referred to as 64,
so 64 deaths per 10,000 people,
that was the highest rate there.
It reduced from that to about 18.6.
And so again, if you're looking
at that saying, "All right,
if I go from the least-fit
category to the most-fit,
my risk goes from 64
deaths per 10,000 people,
down to 18 deaths per 10,000 people."
If that part has confused you,
just run the 18 versus the 64.
So another way to think about that is
if my risk of dying is 18,
and now it all of a
sudden, it goes up to 64,
it's a huge increase in your risk of dying
and nobody wants that.
Similar story for the women,
the numbers there actually went
from the risk per 10,000 was 39.5,
and reduced all the way to 8.5.
And so again, clear evidence
that this thing was happening.
And what's also interesting here,
just because someone will ask, I'm sure,
this was true once they factored out
things like, again, as I mentioned age,
but also smoking habits,
cholesterol levels,
systolic blood pressure,
fasting blood glucose levels,
parental history of
coronary artery disease,
and then follow up, and other metrics.
And so what they're basically saying is,
even if you take those
things into account,
you still see this massive
reduction in health
when we have a reduction
in cardiovascular fitness.
Now I realize following numbers like that
is sometimes difficult
if you're only listening to
this in the audio version,
so we'll have this
paper in the show notes.
The actual title of the paper is
" Physical Fitness and
All-Cause Mortality:
A Prospective Study of
Healthy Men and Women."
And again, first author
Steven Blair from 1989.
So if you cruise onto
Table 2 of that paper,
you're going to see that they
actually ran the analysis
and split up the men and
women into Quintiles.
So this would mean the
lowest 20% of fitness,
the next 20, next 20,
next 20, the next 20.
So take everyone across the
spectrum, lowest to highest,
and split 'em up, top 20%,
et cetera, et cetera, all the way down.
And what I'll read off to
you is the relative risk.
And again, this is risk of dying,
as we go from the most-fit 20 percentile,
to the next most-fit,
to the middle kind of 20%,
to the second to last 20%,
all the way to the bottom 20%,
that's the way to view this.
So if you start at the
highest level of fitness
and we put that as just
a number of 1.0, right?
So this is a saying,
"Okay, you're at a 1.0."
if I go from the top 20 percentile
to the next 20 percentile,
so think of this as like 60
to 80th percent, if you will.
My risk goes from 1 to 1.7.
So this is a 17% increase in risk.
If I go to the next one down,
it's gone from 1 to 1.7 to 1.46.
The next after that, 1.36,
and then here's where it explodes.
So again, think of this as
if you are somewhere between
the 20th to 40th percentile,
100 being the best, 0
being the absolute worst,
so just being the second to last category,
your risk is 1.37.
You go from that category to
the bottom 20th percentile,
so just one category below,
your risk goes from 1.37 to 3.44.
And this is why people will highlight,
you don't have to necessarily
be the fittest on the planet
from a health and
cardiovascular risk perspective,
but you cannot be the lowest.
The magnitude of improvement you see
from going from the
least-fit people around,
to just a second least-fit,
is almost half to three
times the risk reduction.
So massive improvements,
you'll see the exact same
thing in women in this study.
So to not run you through everything,
but we really talking about
improvements as you go from
the healthiest or most-fit,
kind of going all the way down
to the bottom 20th percentile,
that risk factor is 2.42,
and then the lowest goes from 2.42,
all the way up to 4.65.
So a similar message between
the men and the women,
just being the bottom of that category
is incredibly dangerous and
problematic for your health,
so if you can just do a little
bit to bump up one level,
that's going to do a lot for you.
Now again, there's a ton of studies
you could pull from here,
the numbers, again,
I don't want you to be
super specific on that
'cause they will differ
depending upon the population.
A little bit of context on that,
I grabbed another study
for you also in JAMA
far more recently
called "The Association of
Cardio Respiratory Fitness
with Long-Term Mortality Among Adults
Undergoing Exercise Treadmill Testing."
And this is actually going
to tell you a similar story,
but I wanted to show you
how even the studies that
are a little bit different
are going to have the
same take-home message.
In this particular analysis,
now they've got over 122,000 patients.
So okay, great, maybe there was
something unique about Blair
and his little population
of 15,000 people, or so,
what about if we 10 x that number roughly,
do we see the same basic results?
And the answer is effectively yes.
So in this, almost 14,000 people died
throughout the course of this study.
So we're getting same kind of idea,
pretty healthy people,
some are going to die,
but what does it really look like
in terms of the folks that stayed alive
and those that did not?
I'll zoom you all the way down to the end
to not make it so painstaking
as the previous one,
but similar stuff here,
in fact it's even more jarring
because they're able to do
more in-depth analysis here
of some of those other co-factors,
which is what I want to highlight, so.
You know, directly from
the paper again here,
"The increase in all-cause mortality
is associated with reduced
cardiorespiratory fitness,
which was comparable or to or greater
than traditional clinical risk factors,
such as coronary artery
disease, smoking, and diabetes."
Now I am certainly not trying to tell you
that as long as you're in shape
that it's okay if you
smoke or do anything else,
I have nothing of expertise whatsoever
in your actual clinical health,
work through that with your
actual doctor or physician.
Again, just from this
one particular study,
really profound there, right?
The cardiovascular
fitness, again, VO₂ Max,
was more predictive
than traditional risk factors
like coronary artery disease,
smoking, and diabetes, right?
So I'll put numbers behind this
because it gets even more interesting.
"The cardiorespiratory fitness
is inversely associated
with long-term mortality
and not observed to be an upper limit."
What that also means is,
there doesn't seem to be
any reduction in the benefit
by continuing to increase your VO₂ Max.
So in other words,
the higher your VO₂ Max goes,
the more it seems to preserve
all-cause mortality risk.
So there doesn't appear
to be in this study,
in fact, you'd see the same thing
if you looked at almost any
other study in this area,
there seems to be no upper limit.
And so there's just really
not a rationale of saying,
"Well, I'm good enough here,
I'm okay, this is enough,
and if I get any better it
won't really help that much."
You actually do see that
in sport performance.
So a classic example here is
in the sport of mixed martial arts,
if you were to examine the VO₂ Max's
of the athletes in that,
you would see that it's
kind of on an average
of about 55 milliliters
per kilogram per minute,
and if you get past that,
the benefits of performance
continue to go up, but slightly,
and once you really start
getting past north of 65,
it seems to be really no more association
between improved performance,
by that I mean winning fights,
it doesn't mean it is
detrimental, of course,
or not advantageous to
be in better fitness
prior to a mixed martial art fight,
but we're just saying the rate
of increase in performance
against the rate of increase in VO₂ Max
starts to taper off.
We don't see a similar thing
with cardiovascular health.
So hopefully, I've made my point here,
about the importance of VO₂ Max,
but in case I haven't,
just one more final study
that I thought was of interest here,
to bring this point home even more.
Actually, this is one of Jonathan
Myers's more recent papers
called "Cardiorespiratory
Fitness and Mortality Risk
Across the Spectra of Age, Race, and Sex,"
published in the last
couple of years here,
and this is actually
in 750,000 US veterans
between the ages of 30 and 95,
and I like this paper because
the sample size is enormous.
Again, it takes into
account things like race,
as well as age at that spectrum, right?
Almost a 65-year spectrum.
And within that, 175,000
people or so died.
So if it held up against 15,000,
then it held up against 150,000
and now it's holding up against 750,000,
I just don't know
how much more evidence
one would need to see
to believe not only in
this as an actual finding,
but the relative risk ratio
seems to be lining up
across all these studies
as pretty similar.
And so what they found in
this, again, same idea,
they found no reduced
benefit of extreme fitness.
In other words, the higher the VO₂ Max,
just the higher the risk reduction,
there seemed to be no upper limit there.
And in addition, what they
found was a couple of metrics.
So if you take into account
what are called the comorbidities,
and so you look at things like diabetes.
Diabetes in this particular study,
took their risk factor from 1 to 1.34,
so that's a big deal.
However, going from the
highest fitness level
to the next highest fitness level,
represented an increase of risk of 1.66.
So again, I'm not saying
that diabetes is okay
or anything like that,
again, I'm not a medical doctor,
and I don't do really
anything with disease,
but just look how staggering this is.
And in fact, if you run
this all the way out,
examples in this paper,
and here I'm looking at
Figure 2, by the way,
in case you want to go look yourself,
you're talking about the
addition of age represented
a 1.06 increase in risk factor,
hypertension, smoking,
arterial fibrillation, cancer,
all these things are plotted,
and you can see how much
they increased risk,
and all of those, the highest one
was chronic kidney disease,
which represented 1.49.
When you look into the VO₂ Max numbers,
the lowest risk factor was 1.39.
And then it just escalates from there,
to 1.66, to 2.1, to 2.9, again
with the least-fit people
having a 4X higher risk of mortality,
that's how important your heart is.
And so it's hard for me
to make a cogent argument,
that even as athletes
who are interested in,
say again, dunking a basketball
or these anaerobic high
power, low fatigue sports,
very difficult to say, your
heart is not playing a big role
in your global health,
and that that isn't going to limit
your performances somehow.
[music]